Guide to the Maria H. Dehon Polk Collection of Constant Coquelin
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maria H. Dehon Polk collection of Constant Coquelin
1884-1934
GEN MSS 453
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes) + 2 portfolios
Chiefly letters from Coquelin to Maria H. Dehon, including ALS and manuscript transcriptions, and photographs. Also present are a small amount of other correspondence, writings by Coquelin, including an undated holograph of a work on Moliére's Tartuffe, published in 1884, printed materials concerning the Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens, other ephemera, and clippings. Letters from Coquelin, 1894-1908 and undated, concern his friendship with Dehon, their travels, and Coquelin's performances and tours. The letters discuss the Comédie-Français, the Théâtre de la Porte-Saint-Martin, the Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens, and friends and colleagues including Ernest Coquelin, Jean Coquelin, Sarah Bernhardt, Geraldine Farrar, Edmond Rostand, Pierre-Marie-René Waldeck Rousseau, and artist Jean-Charles Cazin. Other correspondence includes letters to Dehon from A. Chabert concerning the establishment of a Musée Cazin-Coquelin. Photographs include cabinet photographs and prints, most portraits of Coquelin, including several portraits in costume as Cyrano de Bergerac and other theater roles. Also present are postcards showing views of Pont-aux-Dames and a set of photographs of paintings of Coquelin in various theater roles.
Polk, Maria H. Dehon, approximately 1857-1941
Coquelin, Constant, 1841-1909
Coquelin, Constant, 1841-1909 ( Tartuffe)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Maria H. Dehon Polk, 1941.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile in portfolio 2 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
CONSTANT COQUELIN (1841-1909) AND MARIA H. DEHON POLK (ca. 1857-1941)
The French actor Constant Coquelin, called Coquelin aîné, was noted for his roles in the plays of Molière and other classical dramatists. He was a member of the Comédie-Française, 1860-1886 and 1890-1892, and toured extensively in Europe and the Americas. In 1897 he created the title role in Edmond Rostand's Cyrano de Bergerac at the Théâtre de la Porte-Saint-Martin, where he served as director. In 1900 he toured the United States with Sarah Bernhardt. Coquelin was the author of works on dramatists and on the art of acting, including L'art et le comédien (1880), Molière et le Misanthrope (1881), and Tartuffe (1884). In 1905 he founded the Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens, a community for retired actors, at Pont-aux-Dames. Coquelin died at Pont-aux-Dames in 1909, while rehearsing Rostand's Chantecler. Both Coquelin's younger brother, Ernest, called Coquelin cadet, and Coquelin's son, Jean, were actors.
Maria H. Dehon was born and lived in New York City, where she was known for her friendships with singers of the Metropolitan Opera. She was associated with Constant Coquelin during her travels in Europe in the 1890s and during his subsequent tours of the United States. They maintained a friendship and correspondence until his death. Dehon married William Mecklenburg Polk, a physician, in 1914. William Mecklenburg Polk died in 1918.
Scope and Contents
The Maria H. Dehon Polk Collection of Constant Coquelin consists of correspondence, photographs, and a small amount of writings, ephemera, clippings, and other printed material. The collection documents Maria H. Dehon's friendship with Coquelin and reflects her interest in his career.
The collection is housed in three boxes and two portfolios and is organized into four series: Letters to Maria H. Dehon Polk, Writings by Constant Coquelin, Printed Material, and Photographs. The portfolios contain Oversize and Restricted Fragile materials.
Series I, Letters to Maria H. Dehon Polk, consists of three subseries, each arranged chronologically: Letters From Constant Coquelin, Transcriptions of Letters From Constant Coquelin, and Letters From Other Correspondents. Letters and transcriptions of letters from Coquelin, in French, 1894-1908 and undated, concern his friendship with Dehon, their travels, and Coquelin's performances and tours. Letters discuss his legal difficulties with the Comédie-Française, his work with the Théâtre de la Porte-Saint-Martin and other theaters, the founding of the Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens, and friends and colleagues including Ernest Coquelin, Jean Coquelin, Sarah Bernhardt, Geraldine Farrar, Edmond Rostand, Pierre-Marie-René Waldeck-Rousseau, and artist Jean-Charles Cazin. Some letters are written on printed or photographic postcards showing portraits of Coquelin or views of the Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens. Transcriptions are written in an unidentified hand and include most of the original letters present in the collection, as well as many additional letters not otherwise present. A few transcriptions were annotated in holograph by Dehon during the 1920s-30s regarding their content. Also present are a few envelopes annotated by Dehon, 1913-1920 and undated, concerning her intentions for disposition of the letters. The third subseries consists of a few letters from A. Chabert, in French, 1910-1934, and Mrs. John Innes Kane, undated. Letters from Chabert concern his interest in memorializing Coquelin and the establishment of a Musée Cazin-Coquelin in Pas-de-Calais.
Series II, Writings by Constant Coquelin, consists of an undated holograph of Coquelin's Tartuffe (published by Paul Ollendorff, Paris, 1884), and a holograph notebook titled "Joseph D'Arimathie, 3eme acte," undated.
Series III, Printed Material, is arranged alphabetically. Material relating to the Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens includes a program for a benefit performance, 1908, and a few promotional items, 1929 and undated. Also present are a program for a benefit for the Society of the Relief of the Destitute Blind, New York, 1901, and newspaper clippings, most concerning Coquelin's death, [1905]-1909 and undated.
Series IV, Photographs, is organized into two subseries: Portraits of Constant Coquelin and Other Photographs. Portraits are cabinet photographs and prints, most undated, several with signatures or inscriptions to Dehon. Included are portraits taken in costume as Cyrano de Bergerac and other theater roles. Other photographs are undated and include a group taken late in Coquelin's life on board a ship with several unidentified people. Also present are postcards showing views of Pont-aux-Dames and a set of photographs of paintings of Coquelin, with a few paintings of Coquelin cadet and Jean Coquelin, in costume in various theater roles. The set is inscribed to Dehon and each photograph is captioned in holograph by Coquelin.
Actors -- France; French drama; Theater -- France; Cabinet photographs; Photographic prints; Actors -- France; Bernhardt, Sarah, 1844-1923; Cazin, Jean-Charles, 1841-1901; Chabert, A.; Coquelin, Constant, 1841-1909; Coquelin, Ernest; Coquelin, Jean, 1865-1944; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967; Molière, 1622-1673 -- Criticism and interpretation; Polk, Maria H. Dehon, approximately 1857-1941; Rostand, Edmond, 1868-1918; Waldeck-Rousseau, Pierre-Marie-René, 1846-1904; Comédie-Française; Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens; Musée Cazin-Coquelin; Théâtre de la Porte-Saint-Martin (Paris, France)
- Letters to Maria H. Dehon Polk, 1894-1934; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Letters to Maria H. Dehon Polk, is organized into three subseries: Letters from Constant Coquelin, Transcriptions of Letters from Constant Coquelin, and Letters from Other Correspondents.
  - LETTERS FROM CONSTANT COQUELIN
    - Letters, 1894-99 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1900-04 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1905-08 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes photographic postcard showing the theater at Pont-aux-Dames
    - Envelopes annotated by Maria H. Dehon Polk, holograph, 1913-20, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - TRANSCRIPTIONS OF LETTERS FROM CONSTANT COQUELIN
    - Letters dated 1894, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters dated 1895, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters dated 1896, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters dated 1897, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters dated 1898, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters dated 1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters dated 1900, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters dated 1901, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters dated 1902, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters dated 1903, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters dated 1904, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters dated 1905 Feb-May, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters dated 1905 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters dated 1906, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letters dated 1907, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters dated 1908, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - LETTERS FROM OTHER CORRESPONDENTS
    - Chabert, A., 1910-34 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Kane, Mrs. John Innes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Writings by Constant Coquelin, [ca. 1884]; Series II; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - "Joseph D'Arimathie, 3eme acte," holograph notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Accompanied by an envelope with brief notes written by Marie H. Dehon Polk, holograph
  - "Tartuffe," holograph, bound volume, [ca. 1884] (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Printed Material, 1901-1929; Series III; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - Brémont, Léon. L'histoire de Pont-aux- Dames (Paris: Vallaz), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Engraved portrait of Moses Mendelssohn (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Entertainment for the Benefit of the Home for the Destitute Blind, Waldorf- Astoria," program, 1901 Apr 12 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Maison de retraite des vieux comédiens. "Programme de la Matinée de gala", 1908 Sep 20 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Newspaper clippings, [1905]-09, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Pour aller à Pont-aux-Dames," promotional map, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Photographs, 1894-1906; Series IV; 0.63; (1.5 box)
  Series IV, Photographs, is organized into two subseries: Portraits of Constant Coquelin and Other Photographs. Portraits are arranged alphabetically by photographer.
  - PORTRAITS OF CONSTANT COQUELIN
    - Boyer, Paul, and Albert Hautecoeur, Paris. Cabinet photograph, as Cyrano de Bergerac (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Chapiro, Saint Petersburg, Russia. Cabinet photograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Dupont, Aimé, New York. Print, inscribed to Dehon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Falk, B. J., New York. Cabinet photograph, as Le Rebbe in L'ami Fritz, signed, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hollyer, Frederick, London. Print (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Nadar, Paris. Print, as Cyrano de Bergerac, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Nadar, Paris. Print, as Cyrano de Bergerac, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified, Argentina. Print, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified. "M. Coquelin aîné dans Hamlet," printed postcard, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified. Photographic postcard, inscribed to Dehon, 1906 Aug 19 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Valleto y Cia., Mexico. Cabinet photograph, inscribed to Dehon, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Walery, Paris. Photographic postcard, in Asian costume, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - OTHER PHOTOGRAPHS
    - 8 prints of CC with several unidentified people on board a ship, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Maison de retraite des artistes dramatiques. 5 printed postcards (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Maison de retraite des artistes dramatiques. Set of 17 printed postcards (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Accompanied by a printed envelope
    - Printed postcard showing a scene in Venice, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - 2 photographic postcards showing scenes in Syria, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Set of mounted prints made by Van Bosch, Paris, of paintings of CC in various costumes, inscribed to Dehon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
    - Original portfolio for prints in folders 49-51, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Oversize
  (1 portfolio)
  - 1 of 8 prints of CC with several unidentified people on board a ship (in Series IV), n.d. (Box Port, folder 53)
- Restricted Fragile
  This portfolio contains fragile originals. The material may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 45 (Box Port, Folder 54)
  - Box 2, folder 30 (Box Port, Folder 55)